Guide to the Frances Faick Walker Papers 1895-1992
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Frances Faick Walker Papers
1895-1992
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 891
Walker, Frances Faick, 1907-1991
1.0 linear foot
Frances Faick Walker was a University of Montana graduate who worked as a social worker in Oregon and collected art as a hobby. This collection contains materials collected by Frances Walker about artists in the Pacific Northwest as well as some information on various members of her family. The collection includes many items from Frances Walker's friendship with Oregon artist Charles Heaney including correspondence, reproductions of his art, photographs, and materials relating to Walker's donation of her collection of Heaney's art to the University of Montana in Missoula.
Biographical Note
Frances Faick was born on June 7, 1907 in Silvercamp, Montana to Conrad and Margaret Faick. Conrad and Margaret Faick would have four children, Helen, Conrad Augustus, Frances, and John. Frances Faick attended the University of Montana in Missoula and graduated in 1931 with a degree in English. She began teaching school and worked in Montana, Washington, and Oregon. She married Clifford Edward Walker in 1941 and the couple resided in Oregon City, Oregon. Frances Faick Walker became a social worker and worked for the Multnomah County Welfare Department and Clackamas County in the Children's Services Division until her retirement in 1972. In her spare time, Frances Walker was also an artist, art collector, and amateur genealogist.
Frances Faick Walker passed away in Clackamas County, Oregon on October 8, 1991.
This collection relates to Frances Walker's donation of artwork to the University of Montana's art museum, now known as the Montana Museum of Art and Culture, as well as her collection of materials related to artist Charles Heaney including personal letters and photographs. It also includes research files on individual artists and some of her research on family history.
The collection is arranged into three series:
Series I: Correspondence, 0.1 linear feet, 1928-1992
Series II: Research Files, 0.4 linear feet, 1895-1975
Series III: Charles Heaney, 0.5 linear feet, 1936-1987
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
These materials remained in the possession of Frances Faick Walker and Clifford Walker until their donation to the University of Montana's School of Fine Arts along with the Walkers' art collection. In 2001, the Museum of Fine Arts, that was administered by the School of Fine Arts and subsequently houses the Walkers' art collection, became a state museum and is now the Montana Museum of Art and Culture (MMAC). In 2015 and 2016 the manuscript materials from the Walker collection were transferred to Archives and Special Collections by the MMAC.
This collection was transferred to Archives and Special Collections from the Montana Museum of Art and Culture at the University of Montana in Missoula.
There are no expected additions to this collection.
Frances Faick Walker and Clifford Walker donated their art collection to the Montana Museum of Art and Culture and the items are part of the museum's permanent collection. Archives and Special Collections also holds the Helen Faick Papers (Mss 858). Helen was Frances Walker's older sister and some of her artwork was included in Frances Walker's donation to the Montana Museum of Art and Culture.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Walker, Frances Faick, 1907-1991--Family; Heaney, Charles, 1897-1981
Montana Museum of Art and Culture; University of Montana--Missoula. Museum of Fine Arts.
Art--Collectors and collecting--Montana--Missoula; Painters--Oregon; Painting, American--Oregon
Fine Arts; Oregon
- Correspondence, 1928-1992; Series I; 0.1 linear feet
  This series contains correspondence to and from Frances Walker and her husband, Clifford Walker. It includes letters and cards from friends and exchanges between the University of Montana School of Fine Arts and the Walkers as they were preparing to donate their art collection to the University.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Brown, James Mason and Catherine, 1958-1965 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Christmas Cards, 1958-1972 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Grover, Ruth, 1988 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Merriam, H.G., 1950-1980 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Shope, Shorty and Erva, 1928-1979 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - University of Montana School of Fine Arts, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Research Files, 1895-1975; Series II; 0.4 linear feet
  This series contains materials collected by Frances Walker during her research of her family history as well as information she gathered about various artists who lived and worked in the Pacific Northwest.
  - Faick, Conrad Augustus, 1931-1949 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Faick, John, 1933-1963 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Jackson, Helen Lacaff, 1895 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - McCosh, David, undated (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Runquist, Albert, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Russell, Charlie, 1932 and undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Salish, Flathead Photos, 1927-1932 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Schwalm, F.D., 1920 (Box-folder 1/14)
- Charles Heaney, 1936-1987; Series III; 0.5 linear feet
  This series contains materials collected by Frances Walker from various aspects of artist Charles Heaney's life and her friendship with him. These materials include publicity for art openings, photographs, correspondence between Heaney and the Walkers, a recorded interview with Heaney, reproductions of Heaney's art, and additional ephemera collected by the Walkers including Heaney's obituary and photos of his home.
  Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Publicity, Articles, 1936-1987 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Slides, 1965-1976 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Photographs, 1965-1981 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Lettering and Cards, 1966-1981 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Correspondence about Art, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Reproductions and Photographs of Art, 1976-1987 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Interview, Audiocassettes, May 22, 1978 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Obituaries, Remembrances, Chronology, Art Information, 1979-1986 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Letter from Sue Jones to Charles Heaney, 1981 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Photographs of Charles Heaney's Home, 1981 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Photographs and Negatives of Art, undated (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Photographs of Art by Bill Grand, undated (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Slideshow Description, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
    There are no slides accompanying this description, possibly from a lecture on Heaney's art.